Sustainability represents
تمثّل الإستدامة
the what, the where and the how
ماذا وأين وأقل
of what is caught.
ما يمكن صيده.
The who and the why are what's important to me.
ما يشغل بالي هو من ولماذا.
I want to know the people behind my dinner choices.
أريد أن أعرف الناس الذين يتناولون وجباتي.
I want to know how I impact them.
أرغب بمعرفة تأثيري عليهم.
I want to know how they impact me.
وأن أعرف كيف يؤثرون عليّ.
I want to know why they fish.
أريد أن أعرف كيفية صيدهم.
I want to know how they rely on the water's bounty
أريد أن أعرف كيفية إعتمادهم على سخاء المياه
for their living.
في حياتهم.
Understanding all of this enables us
إن فهم كل هذا يمكننا
to shift our perception of seafood
من تغيير تصوراتنا للأطعمة البحرية
away from a commodity
من كونها سلع
to an opportunity
إلى فرصة
to restore our ecosystem.
لإستعادة نظامنا البيئي .
It allows for us to celebrate the seafood
إنها تتيح لنا الإحتفاء بالأطعمة البحرية
that we're also so fortunate to eat.
التي نحن مرفهون بأكلها.
So what do we call this?
إذاً ما هو مسمى هذا؟
I think we call it restorative seafood.
أعتقد أننا نسميه بالمأكولات البحرية التصالحية.
Where sustainability is the capacity
حيث تكون الإستدامة هي المقدرة
to endure and maintain,
على التحمل والمحافظة،
restorative is the ability to replenish and progress.
التصالحية هي القدرة على التجديد والتقدم.
Restorative seafood allows for an evolving and dynamic system
تسمح المأكولات البحرية التصالحية بنظام متطور نامي وديناميكي
and acknowledges our relationship with the ocean
وتعترف بعلاقتنا بالمحيطات
as a resource,
كمورد
suggesting that we engage to replenish the ocean
مقترحة بانخراطنا في تجديد موارد المحيطات
and to encourage its resiliency.
وتشجيع مرونتها.
It is a more hopeful, it is a more human,
إنها مفعمة بالأمل أكثر ، إنها أكثر إنسانية
and is a more useful way of understanding our environment.
وطريقة أكثر فائدة لفهم بيئتنا.
Wallet guides -- standard issue
أدلة المحافظ -- الموضوع القياسي
by lots in the marine conservation world --
لكثير من مجتمعات المحافظة على البحار--
are very handy; they're a wonderful tool.
إنها أداة مفيدة ورائعة حقاً.
Green, yellow and red lists [of] seafood species.
قوائم حمراء وصفراء وخضراء لأطعمة البحار.
The association is very easy: buy green, don't buy red,
العلاقة سهلة جداً: أشتري الأخضر، لا تشتري الأحمر،
think twice about yellow.
وفكّر مرتين قبل شراء الأصفر.
But in my mind, it's really not enough
لكن برأيي، ذلك ليس كافياً
to just eat green list.
أن نأكل قائمة خضراء فقط.
We can't sustain this without the measure of our success
لا يمكننا إستدامة هذا بدون مقاييس لنجاحنا
really changing the fate of the species
في تغيير مصائر الكائنات
in the yellow and the red.
في القائمة الصفراء والحمراء.
But what if we eat only in the green list?
لكن مالذي سيحدث إن أكلنا القائمة الخضراء فقط؟
You've got pole-caught yellowfin tuna here --
لديك سمكة تونا صفراء تم صيدها من القطب هنا--
comes from sustainable stocks.
تأتي من مخزونات مستدامة.
Pole caught -- no bycatch.
تم صيدها من القطب -- ليس عرضياً.
Great for fishermen. Lots of money. Supporting local economies.
صفقة عظيمة للغاية للصيادين. الكثير من المال. تدعم الإقتصادات المحلية.
But it's a lion of the sea. It's a top predator.
لكنه أسد البحر. إنها الأكثر إفتراساً.
What's the context of this meal?
ما هو سياق هذه الوجبة؟
Am I sitting down in a steakhouse to a 16-ounce portion of this?
هل أجلس أنا في مطعم لأكل قطعة تزن 16 أوقية من هذا؟
Do I do this three times a week?
هل أفعل هذا ثلاث مرات أسبوعياً؟
I might still be in the green list,
ربما أبقى في القائمة الخضراء؟
but I'm not doing myself, or you,
لكني لا أفعل أي شئ حسن لنفسي
or the oceans any favors.
أو لك أو للمحيطات
The point is that we have to have a context,
الفكرة هي أنه يتوجب علينا النظر للسياق،
a gauge for our actions in all this.
كمقياس لأعمالنا في كل هذا.
Example: I've heard that red wine is great for my health --
على سبيل المثال: سمعت أن النبيذ الأحمر جيد للصحة--
antioxidants and minerals -- heart healthy.
مضاد الأكسدة والمعادن-- صحة للقلب.
That's great! I love red wine!
ذلك عظيم! أنا أحب النبيذ الأحمر!
I'm going to drink so much of it. I'm going to be so healthy.
سأشرب الكثير منه. وسأكون بصحة جيدة.
Well, how many bottles is it
حسناً، كم من هذه القوارير
before you tell me that I have a problem?
ستنفد قبل أن تخبروني أن لدي مشكلة؟
Well folks, we have a protein problem.
حسناً يا رفاق، إن لدينا مشكلة بروتينات.
We have lost this sensibility
لقد فقدنا هذه الحساسية
when it regards our food,
حينما يتعلق الأمر بطعامنا،
and we are paying a cost.
ونحن ندفع الثمن.
The problem is we are hiding that cost beneath the waves.
المشكلة هي أننا نخفي الثمن تحت الأمواج.
We are hiding that cost
نحن نخفي تلك التكلفة
behind the social acceptance of expanding waistlines.
خلف القبول الإجتماعي لتوسيع الخصر.
And we are hiding that cost behind monster profits.
ونحن نخفي التكلفة خلف الأرباح الوحشية.
So the first thing about this idea of restorative seafood
لذا فأول شئ عن فكرة الوجبات البحرية التصالحية هذه
is that it really takes into account our needs.
هي أنها تأخذ إحتياجاتنا في الحسبان.
Restorative seafood might best be represented
إن أفضل طريقة لتمثيل الطعام البحري التصالحي ربما،
not by Jaws, or by Flipper, or the Gordon's fisherman,
ليس عبر الفكين أو الزعنفة، أو صائد الغردون،
but rather, by the Jolly Green Giant.
بل عبر جولي الأخضر العملاق.
Vegetables:
الخضروات:
they might yet save the oceans.
ربما لا تنقذ المحيطات.
Sylvia likes to say that blue is the new green.
تحب سيلفيا القول أن الأزرق (المحيطات) هي الخضرة الجديدة.
Well I'd like to respectfully submit
حسناً بكل إحترام أريد القول أن
that broccoli green might then be the new blue.
ذلك القرنبيط الأخضر ربما يكون الأزرق الجديد.
We must continue to eat
يجب أن نستمر بأكل
the best seafood possible, if at all.
أفضل الأطعمة البحرية الممكنة، على كل حال.
But we also must eat it with a ton of vegetables.
لكن أيضاً يجب أن نأكلها مع أطنان من الخضروات.
The best part about restorative seafood though
إن أفضل جزء لأطعمة البحار التصالحية
is that it comes on the half-shell
هي أنها تأتي مع نصف قوقعة
with a bottle of Tabasco and lemon wedges.
مع قارورة من تاباسكو وأسافين الليمون.
It comes in a five-ounce portion of tilapia
إنها تأتي مع خمس أوقيات من البلطي
breaded with Dijon mustard and crispy, broiled breadcrumbs
المخبوز مع خردل الديجون المموج
and a steaming pile of pecan quinoa pilaf
والبقسماط المشوي وكومة مبخرة
with crunchy, grilled broccoli
من بيلاو الكينوا البقان مع القرنبيط
so soft and sweet and charred and smoky on the outside
ناعم جداً وطاعم ومتفحم ومبخر من الخارج
with just a hint of chili flake.
مع القليل من الفلفل الحار.
Whooo!
أووووه!
This is an easy sell.
هذا بيع سهل.
And the best part is all of those ingredients are available
وأفضل جزء هو أن كل هذه المكونات موجودة
to every family at the neighborhood Walmart.
لكل أسرة في متجر وول مارت في الحي.
Jamie Oliver is campaigning
يقوم جيمي أوليفر بحملة
to save America from the way we eat.
لإنقاذ أمريكا من الطريقة التي نأكل بها.
Sylvia is campaigning to save the oceans
تقوم سيلفيا بحملة لإنقاذ المحيطات
from the way we eat.
من الطريقة التي نأكل بها.
There's a pattern here.
هناك نمط متسلسل هنا.
Forget nuclear holocaust;
أنسوا المحرقة النووية.
it's the fork that we have to worry about.
إنها الشوكة التي يجب أن نقلق بشأنها.
We have ravaged our Earth
لقد قمنا بتدمير الأرض
and then used the food that we've sourced
ثم استخدمنا الطعام الذي أنتجناه
to handicap ourselves in more ways than one.
لتقويض أنفسنا بأكثر من طريقة.
So I think we have this whole eating thing wrong.
لذا أعتقد أن كل الطرق التي نأكل بها خاطئة.
And so I think it's time
وأعتقد أنه قد حان الوقت
we change what we expect from our food.
لتغيير ما نتوقعه من طعامنا.
Sustainability is complicated
الإستدامة عملية معقدة،
but dinner is a reality that we all very much understand.
لكن العشاء هي الحقيقة التي ينبغي أن ندركها بشدة،
So let's start there.
لذا لنبدأ من هناك.
There's been a lot of movement recently in greening our food systems.
كانت هناك الكثير من الحركات التي تساند الخضرة في نظامنا الغذائي مؤخراً.
Dan Barber and Alice Waters
الطاه دان باربر وأليس واترس
are leading passionately the green food Delicious Revolution.
يقودان ثورة الطعام الأخضر اللذيذ بكل شغف.
But green foods often represent
لكن الأطعمة الخضراء يتم تمثيلها عادة
a way for us to disregard
بطرق لا تجعلنا نعتبر
the responsibility as eaters.
أن هناك مسؤولية للمتناولين.
Just because it comes from a green source
فقط لأنه يأتي من مصادر خضراء
doesn't mean we can treat it with disregard on the plate.
لا يعني أن بامكاننا معاملته بدون إعتبار للصحن.
We have eco-friendly shrimp.
لدينا جمبري صديق للبيئة.
We can make them; we have that technology.
يمكننا صنعه. فلدينا التكنلوجيا.
But we can never have any eco-friendly all-you-can-eat shrimp buffet.
لكن لا يمكننا مطلقاً الحصول على أي بوفيه صديق للبيئة كل ما فيه من الجمبري.
It doesn't work.
الأمر لا ينجح.
Heart-healthy dinner is a very important part
العشاء الصحي للقلب هو جزء مهم
of restorative seafood.
من أطعمة البحار التصالحية.
While we try to manage declining marine populations,
بينما نحاول إدارة التدهور في كائنات البحار،
the media's recommending increased consumption of seafood.
تنصح وسائل الإعلام بزيادة إستهلاك الأطعمة البحرية.
Studies say that tens of thousands
تقول الدراسات أن عشرات الآلاف
of American grandmothers, grandfathers, mothers and fathers
من الجدود والجدات الأمريكيين، الأمهات والآباء
might be around for another birthday
ربما يولدوا من جديد
if we included more seafood.
إذا أكلوا طعاماً بحرياً أكثر في وجباتهم.
That's a reward I am not willing to pass up.
ذلك هو الجزاء الذي لا أرغب في تمريره.
But it's not all about the seafood.
لكن الأمر ليس فقط عن الاطعمة البحرية.
It's about the way that we look at our plates.
إنه متعلق بالطريقة التي ننظر بها لصحوننا.
As a chef, I realize the easiest thing for me to do
كوني طاه، لقد أدركت أسهل الطرق بالنسبة لي هي
is reduce the portion sizes on my plate.
تقليل أحجام الأجزاء في صحني.
A couple things happened.
حدثت عدة أشياء.
I made more money.
لقد جنيت أموال أكثر.
People started buying appetizers and salads,
بدأ الناس يشترون المقبلات والسلطة،
because they knew they weren't going to fill up on the entrees alone.
لأنهم عرفوا أنهم لن يشبعوا من الاطباق الرئيسية فحسب
People spent more time engaging in their meals,
قضى الناس أوقاتاً أكثر أثناء تناول وجباتهم،
engaging with each other over their meals.
مشاركين مع بعضهم البعض في الاكل.
People got, in short, more of what they came there for
باختصار حصل الناس على أكثر مما جاءوا من أجله،
even though they got less protein.
رغماً عن حصولهم على بروتين أقل.
They got more calories over the course of a diversified meal.
حصلوا على سعرات حرارية أكثر خلال تناول وجباتهم المتنوعة.
They got healthier. I made more money.
وأصبحوا أكثر صحة. وجنيت أموال أكثر.
This is great.
هذا عظيم.
Environmental consideration was served with every plate,
ومع مراعاة الجوانب البيئية لكل صحن،
but it was served with a heaping mound
لكن تقديمها كان مع كومة كبيرة
of consideration for human interests at the same time.
من الإعتبارات للمصالح الإنسانية في نفس الوقت.
One of the other things we did
أحد الأشياء الأخرى التي فعلناها
was begin to diversify the species that we served --
كانت البدء بتنويع الكائنات التي نقدمها --
small silverfish, anchovies, mackerel, sardines were uncommon.
السردين الفضي الصغير، الماكريل، السردين كان الأكثر.
Shellfish, mussels, oysters,
القواقع، بلح البحر، المحار،
clams, tilapia, char -- these were the common species.
البلطي، الشار، -- كانت هذه أطباق شائعة.
We were directing tastes
كنا نوجّه الأذواق
towards more resilience, more restorative options.
تجاه خيارات أكثر مرونة وتصالحية.
This is what we need to favor.
هذا ما نحن بحاجة لدعمه.
This is what the green list says.
هذا ما تقوله القائمة الخضراء.
But this is also how we can actually begin to restore our environment.
لكن هذا أيضاً كيف يمكننا بدء إستعادة بيئتنا.
But what of those big predators,
لكن ماذا عن تلك المفترسات الضخمة،
those fashionable species,
تلك الكائنات المألوفة،
that green list tuna that I was talking about earlier?
قائمة التونة الخضراء التي تحدثت عنها سابقاً؟
Well, if you must, I have a recipe for you.
حسناً، إن كان لابد، فلدي الوصفة لكم.
It pretty much works with any big fish in the ocean,
إنها تعمل مع أي سمكة ضخمة في المحيط،
so here we go.
وها هي.
Start with a 16-ounce portion of big fish.
أبدأ بقطعة 16 أوقية من السمكة الضخمة.
Get a knife. Cut it into four portions.
خذ سكيناً. أقطعها لأربعة أجزاء.
Put it on four plates.
ضعها على أربعة من الأطباق.
Mound up those four plates with vegetables
أملأ تلك الأطباق بالخضروات
and then open up the very best bottle of Burgundy you have,
ثم أفتح أفضل قارورة من البورجوندي لديك،
light the candles and celebrate it.
قم بإضاءة الشموع وأحتفي بها.
Celebrate the opportunity you have to eat this.
أحتفي بالفرصة التي لديك لأكل هذا.
Invite your friends and neighbors over
أدعو أصدقائك وجيرانك
and repeat once a year,
وقم بتكرار هذا ، ربما
maybe.
مرة سنوياً،
I expect a lot from food.
أتوقع الكثير من الطعام.
I expect health
أتوقع الصحة
and joy and family and community.
والمتعة والأسرة والمجتمع.
I expect that producing ingredients,
أتوقع أن إنتاج المكونات
preparing dishes and eating meals
وتحضير الاطباق وأكل الوجبات
is all part of the communion of human interests.
كلها أجزاء من التواصل لمصالح البشر.
I was lucky enough that my father was a fantastic cook.
كنت محظوظاً بما يكفي بأن والدي كان طباخاً ماهراً.
And he taught me very early on
وقد علمني منذ الصبا
about the privilege that eating represents.
عن الإمتياز الذي يمثله الطعام.
I remember well the meals of my childhood.
أذكر جيداً الوجبات أثناء طفولتي.
They were reasonable portions of protein
لقد كانت كمية كافية من البروتين
served with copious quantities of vegetables
تم تقديمها مع كميات من الاخبطوط والخضروات
and small amounts of starch, usually rice.
وكميات صغيرة من النشويات، عادة من الأرز.
This is still how I largely eat today.
هذا في الغالب ما أكله اليوم.
I get sick when I go to steakhouses.
أصاب بالإعياء عندما أذهب لمتاجر الستيك.
I get the meat sweats.
أتعرق جراء اللحوم.
It's like a hangover from protein.
إنه مثل رحلة قنص للبروتينات.
It's disgusting.
إنها مقززة.
But of all the dire news that you'll hear
لكن كل الاخبار الخطيرة التي ستسمعونها
and that you have heard about the state of our oceans,
وأنكم ستسمعون عن حالة المحيطات،
I have the unfortunate burden of delivering to you
فلدي بكل أسف عبء إخباركم
possibly the very worst of it
بأسواء ما فيها
and that is this whole time
وأن طوال هذا الوقت،
your mother was right.
كانت والدتك على حق.
Eat your vegetables.
قم بأكل الخضروات.
It's pretty straightforward.
الأمر مباشر للغاية.
So what are we looking for in a meal?
إذاً إلى ماذا نتطلع للوجبات؟
Well for health, I'm looking for wholesome ingredients
حسناً للصحة، فأنا أتطلع للمكونات الجيدة
that are good for my body.
المفيدة لجسدي.
For joy, I'm looking for butter and salt
للمتعة، أنا أتطلع الزبدة والملح
and sexy things that make things taste less like penance.
والأشياء المثيرة التي تجعل المذاق مثل التكفير عن الذنب.
For family, I'm looking for recipes
للأسرة، أنا أتطلع لوصفة
that genuflect to my own personal histories.
تعكس تواريخي الشخصية.
For community though, we start at the very beginning.
للمجتمع، نبدأ من البداية الأولى.
There's no escaping the fact
لا توجد حقيقة يمكن الإلتفاف عليها
that everything we eat has a global impact.
بأن أي شئ نأكله لديه تأثير كوني.
So try and learn as best you can what that impact is
ونحاول تعلم أفضل ما نستطيع عن تأثيره
and then take the first step to minimize it.
ثم نأخذ زمام المبادرة لتقليل ذلك التأثير.
We've seen an image of our blue planet,
لقد رأينا صوراً لكوكبنا الأزرق،
our world bank.
بنكنا الدولي.
But it is more than just a repository of our resources;
لكن أكثر من مجرد مخزن لمواردنا.
it's also the global geography
إنه كذلك الجغرافيا الكوني
of the communion we call dinner.
للتواصل الذي نسميه وجبة عشاء.
So if we all take only what we need,
لذا إن أخذنا جميعاً ما نحتاجه،
then we can begin to share the rest,
حينها سنبدأ بتقاسم المتبقي،
we can begin to celebrate,
ويمكننا أن نبدأ الإحتفال،
we can begin to restore.
يمكننا أن نبدأ الإستعادة.
We need to savor vegetables.
نحتاج لتذوق الخضروات.
We need to savor smaller portions of seafood.
نحتاج لتذوق أجزاء أقل من الأطعمة البحرية.
And we need to save dinner.
نحتاج للحفاظ على العشاء.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)